<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss xmlns:iweb="http://www.apple.com/iweb" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Filming</title>
    <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/animation-restoration/Filming</link>
    <description>Early animation techniques used by Disney in the late 1930s to 1950&#x2019;s were at the forefront of innovation in terms of color and filming technology.  Click on the short articles below to read about some of these technologies and how the the studio&#x2019;s filming choices laid the groundwork for how archival work and restoration is approached today.</description>
    <item>
      <title>CinemaScope and Technirama</title>
      <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/animation-restoration/Filming/Entries/2007/3/27_CinemaScope_and_Technirama.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">ed251b04-0f29-41f9-8b73-6a1f02617e4a</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2007 19:44:52 -0400</pubDate>
      <description>In the 1950&#x2019;s, the advent of television caused a surge of new technologies aimed at distinguishing the cinema experience as unique and exclusive.  On his blisteringly comprehensive website devoted to the history of widescreen cinema, Martin Hart debunks the notion that this was the only factor that led to the growth of these technologies:</description>
      <iweb:comment enabled="0" count="0" link="https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/animation-restoration/Filming/Entries/2007/3/27_CinemaScope_and_Technirama.html#comment_layer"></iweb:comment>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Multiplane Camera</title>
      <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/animation-restoration/Filming/Entries/2007/2/12_The_Multiplane_Camera.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">a92f9651-d117-455b-a182-b86c7b8db9a4</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2007 21:05:27 -0500</pubDate>
      <description>In the tradition of what he called &amp;quot;our school of self-improvement,&amp;quot;1 Walt Disney patented the Multiplane camera on November 16,1936, with the help of inventor William E. Garity.  The purpose of the camera was to create an illusion of realistic depth that was not previously possible in flat 2-D animation. In the behind-the-scenes featurette Tricks of the Trade, originally broadcast on television show in 1957, Walt explained the process and illustrated the way animators traditionally created depth. With clips for illustration, the piece shows how the traditional methods work for certain scenes, such as a pan with one character walking left to right across a relatively simple background. According to a 1938 article in American Cinematographer,&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</description>
      <iweb:image href="Media/multiplane%20walt%20hand.jpg"></iweb:image>
      <iweb:comment enabled="0" count="0" link="https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/animation-restoration/Filming/Entries/2007/2/12_The_Multiplane_Camera.html#comment_layer"></iweb:comment>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Successive Exposure and &#x201C;Three-strip&#x201D; Technicolor</title>
      <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/animation-restoration/Filming/Entries/2007/2/12_Successive_Exposure_and_Three-strip_Technicolor.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">c9e5c2e4-5d87-4fc8-96d8-41809bd51b56</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2007 21:04:38 -0500</pubDate>
      <description>Color is a factor that many modern consumers take for granted, but the early years of the development of color technology were a period of great innovation and creativity on the part of the engineers who invented these processes.  Color is especially important for animation, for which the capacity to represent realistic situations is limited by the drawn image.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many color processes came and went throughout the first 50 years of film technology, some of which included Kinemacolor, Primsacolor, Multicolor, and Cinecolor.1  When Technicolor modified its two-color techniques into a revolutionary three-color system, the goal of reaching truly realistic color schemes on the film screen started to become a reality, and every producer wanted to utilize the technique, including Disney.  Disney and Technicolor founder Herbert Kalmus signed a contract giving Disney a five-year exclusive rights for five years to use the process, but this was shortened to one year by pressure from the other studios, who were not thrilled about the prospect of being left behind in the ashes of the two-color processes they were allowed to use.2&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Disney shot the first short that utilized three-strip color with the Silly Symphony short Flowers and Trees.  Scott Higgins quotes Kalmus in an article that details how Technicolor used animation as a tool to sell the product to other producers,&lt;br/&gt;</description>
      <iweb:image href="Media/snow%20white%20well.jpg"></iweb:image>
      <iweb:comment enabled="0" count="0" link="https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/animation-restoration/Filming/Entries/2007/2/12_Successive_Exposure_and_Three-strip_Technicolor.html#comment_layer"></iweb:comment>
    </item>
    <iweb:dateFormat>EEEE, MMMM d, yyyy</iweb:dateFormat>
    <iweb:baseURL>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/animation-restoration/Filming</iweb:baseURL>
    <iweb:maximumSummaryItems>5</iweb:maximumSummaryItems>
  </channel>
</rss>
