<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content collectionGUID="CBFD8CBB-F2EC-4147-B62D-881FA8511E8F">
  <lastEdited clientType="local-build-20210826" date="2021-08-26 14:40:10 -0400"/>
  <textBox id="generic-title-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>&lt;b&gt;Basic Facts&lt;/b&gt;</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-body-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>&#x2022;	Worked first in the ink and paint department, then operating the animation camera, then as an in-betweener assisting Iwerks, first on Oswald the Lucky Rabbit&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;	When Universal threatened to take away the Oswald rights, they courted and successfully stole many of Walt&#x2019;s key animators.  Les Clark was not among them due to being lower in the ranks.  After this, he rose in the ranks at the studio, assisting Iwerks with all three of the early Mickey shorts (&lt;i&gt;Plane Crazy, Gallopin&#x2019; Gaucho &lt;/i&gt;and &lt;i&gt;Steamboat Willie&lt;/i&gt;).&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;   Iwerks had resisted the key-pose method which would require that he draw broad sketches of actions and have an in-betweener fill them in, but later deferred to Walt so that they could turn out a product more quickly.  As his assistant, Clark quickly began animating on his own, and got a crash course in drawing Mickey Mouse.&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;	&lt;i&gt;Steamboat Willie&lt;/i&gt; was a success due to the synchronization of music to actions, and after that (in 1929) the studio starting pumping out Silly Symphonies in bulk, with Clark animating.  His first Symphony was &lt;i&gt;Skeleton Dance &lt;/i&gt;(1929).&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;	Clark would take art classes at night beginning in 1929 when Walt started offering them after hours at the studio.  According to Frank Thomas, he was the only animator who continued to take these classes throughout his career.&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;	Fred Moore started as Clark&#x2019;s assistant in 1930, and soon afterward redesigned Mickey Mouse into a closer version of the form we see him in today.&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;	After Ub Iwerks left the studio, Clark became a Mickey expert, and taught a seminar to the newer animators in the summer of 1936, about Mickey&#x2019;s personality and how to draw his character.&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;	Clark was a key animator on two Silly Symphonies that were infamous &#x201C;test subjects&#x201D; for later works.  These include &lt;i&gt;Flowers and Trees&lt;/i&gt; (the first animated film in Technicolor), and &lt;i&gt;The Goddess of Spring&lt;/i&gt; (for which the animators were testing out the movements for a female character prior to starting &lt;i&gt;Snow White&lt;/i&gt;).&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;	Clark was also a key animator on &lt;i&gt;Snow White&lt;/i&gt;, and after that film caused the production of features to take off, he worked on nearly every major feature (with the exception of &lt;i&gt;Bambi&lt;/i&gt;) through &lt;i&gt;The Sword in the Stone&lt;/i&gt; in 1963.  He continued to work on shorts throughout this time.&#xD;&#xD;&#x2022;	Even though he did not retire until 1975, his last twelve years at the studio were spent directing countless informational and educational films, such as &lt;i&gt;Donald&#x2019;s Fire Survival Plan&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Goofy&#x2019;s Freeway Trouble&lt;/i&gt; (1965), &lt;i&gt;I&#x2019;m No Fool with Electricity &lt;/i&gt;(1970) and &lt;i&gt;VD Attack Plan&lt;/i&gt; (1975).&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;Quotes by and about Clark:&#xD;&#xD;&#x201C;Early in his career he was known for animating smoothly rhythmic (&#x201C;ripple&#x201D;) actions that repeat in pleasing cycles and patterns of motion.  &#x2018;The came out of working on the Silly Symphonies,&#x2019; explained Clark in a late interview, &#x2018;which was rhythmic to music and to a musical beat for most of it.  Walt gave me an awful lot of rhythm animation to do, so I guess he liked it.&#x2019;&#x201D; &#xD;[John Canemaker, &lt;i&gt;Walt&#x2019;s Disney&#x2019;s Nine Old Men and the Art of Animation &lt;/i&gt;(London: Turnaround, 2002): 14-15]&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;(Christopher Finch) Can you tell me what one of your most difficult assignments was?&#xD;&#xD;(Clark) Most of them are when you get started.  There are always different problems to work out.  That&#x2019;s a very tough question to ask because as we grow, and more was demanded of us, or asked of us, rather; as animation became more and more developed, refined &#x2026;&#x201D;&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;Well, Walt wasn&#x2019;t always very flattering, because I don&#x2019;t think he thought it was good psychology to flatter.  But he did let you know if he liked something.  The Sugarplum Fairies pleased him somewhat.  I did the first part, and I took the concept of a hummingbird darting back and forth, and it made it an action that was quite different.&#x201D;&#xD;&#xD;[Both quotes above were from an interview with Christopher Finch in July 1973 - from the John Canemaker Animation Archives]&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;In regard to Mickey&#x2019;s personality, Clark remarked that in the two scenes just mentioned, Mickey was frustrated, and this gave Clark an opening into his personality.  Clark believes that Mickey&#x2019;s personality reflected Walt&#x2019;s primarily through the voice, which Walt provided.  He also believes that Mickey was derived in part from Chaplin.  Walt was &#x201C;very fond of Chaplin.&#x201D;&#xD;&#xD;[notes by Michael Barrier after an interview with Clark in 1973 - from the John Canemaker Animation Archives]&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;(about animating Pinocchio&#x2019;s character)&#xD;We had to make him act like a wooden character &#x2026; by staying away from the rubbery action.  There was a joint here &#x2013; his hand to his wrist, his elbow to his forearm, and so forth, so we just animated in those stages &#x2026; more sharply defined.  &#xD;&#xD;&#xD;You&#x2019;d think after animating a lot of years, you could take any scene or any character and do what you wanted with it, but every scene was a challenge.  Even the character could get off what you wanted.  Even today it&#x2019;s the same.  Otherwise, it&#x2019;s stereotyped stuff.&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;Fergy was a very loose animator; his  roughs were very rough &#x2026; Burt Gillett, Jack King were tighter animators.  I think as we progressed, and learned to draw a little better, it evolved into a combination of a looseness that Fergy had (with the Iwerks style) I think &#x2026; the early 30&#x2019;s, from &#x2019;31 to &#x2019;35 or so was sort of a melding of all these styles.  And this was due to Walt &#x2013; if he didn&#x2019;t like that animation, he&#x2019;d tell you so, or if it was too loose, he&#x2019;d say, try it this way or that way.  He directed the type of animation he wanted.&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;(Mike Barrier) In the early days of Mickey Mouse, were there any footage requirements for the animators?&#xD;&#xD;(Clark) We went through different systems.  We had an economy expert actually come in and try to measure your pencil mileage; that didn&#x2019;t work out. Then there was a time when Walt would classify the animation as A, B or C quality, and you would get a bonus if you did A, B or C and did it faster than the time was allowed.  Of course, I resented all that.  So naturally, I didn&#x2019;t make many bonuses.&#xD;&#xD;[The four quotes above were from an interview with Mike Barrier in December 1973 - from the John Canemaker Animation Archives]&#xD;&#xD;Maybe one thing to tell them is to be observant on everything they see that moves; to record it in their mind and to see it in a more comical way.  But basically to be observant.  I know that is what Walt always used to tell us.  Anything you see, why, record it in your memory, so sometime you may have to use it.  I still do it now.  Even if I see a funny run or a funny walk or something, or see a person walking in a certain manner.&#xD;&#xD;[From an interview with Frank Thomas in July 1978 - from the John Canemaker Animation Archives]&#xD;&#xD;&#xD;</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-datefield-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>&lt;b&gt;Sunday, June 10, 2007&lt;/b&gt;</richText>
  </textBox>
  <image id="generic-picture-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes" src="11_Basic_Facts_files/shapeimage_2.png" left="0px" top="0px" width="400px" height="300px"/>
</content>
