<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:iweb="http://www.apple.com/iweb" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Paper Excerpts</title>
    <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Paper_Excerpts.html</link>
    <description>I used excerpted sections from three papers and one written project to illustrate what I believe are the core concepts articulated in my introduction.  Click on the links below to view the excerpts.</description>
    <generator>iWeb 3.0.2</generator>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Paper_Excerpts_files/homeland%20cover.jpg</url>
      <title>Paper Excerpts</title>
      <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Paper_Excerpts.html</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Light My Fire: Video Furnace and online access  for moving image archives</title>
      <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2008/3/14_Light_My_Fire__Video_Furnace_and_online_access_for_moving_image_archives.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">d454317c-25c4-4cac-ae6a-eec441fd185a</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2008 15:24:21 -0400</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2008/3/14_Light_My_Fire__Video_Furnace_and_online_access_for_moving_image_archives_files/quicktime.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Media/object455_1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding-right:10px; padding-bottom:10px; width:251px; height:188px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For the Access to Moving Image Collections class (MIAS 250), the midterm consisted of a two-part paper discussing the situation at UCLA’s Instructional Media Collections and Services (IMCS).  The IMCS is preparing for a major overhaul on their access center, the Instructional Media Lab (IML).  The first half of the midterm was an analysis and suggested improvements for the new IML.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The second half of the midterm, included below, was an evaluation of the legality and practicality of using a video delivery vendor, Video Furnace, to stream moving image material from IMCS collections to students.  The paper needed to base the current IMCS situation in the larger context of streaming content for moving image archives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We need to have a conversation about the legal regime in which we would like to live, and then do what we can to help bring that world into being. &lt;br/&gt;– Rick Prelinger [1]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No one wants to conduct research at the library anymore.  Students write papers based only on what they can find on the web.   If a film or video clip isn’t online, no one cares if it exists.  As inflammatory and simplistic as the above three statements are, all three reflect realities that can be backed up by current literature across the fields of library and archival studies, critical studies and mainstream publications.  And doubtless anyone who reads them will feel a strange combination of concurrence, remorse, and inspiration to change the reality they represent.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In a current age of clearance culture, moving image archives are stuck between what Jack Valenti has called the race between “the delivery dream and the piracy nightmare.” [2] It is difficult to envision a community of online archives with joyously streaming, easily accessible content for all.  In a recent report, David Pierce outlines a strategy for archives to develop an online presence by identifying content that is not restricted by copyright or other permissions, and then created curated access points to that content, similar to the model of the Internet Archive; “curated websites are the best way to deliver content because they provide multiple points of entry for novice users, while still providing content for the experienced researcher.” [3]  But even this carries the potential for backlash.  Archivists still must consider the privacy of represented people, places and situations.  Archives with significant collections of amateur works and home movies face the potential risk of exposing personal details of the lives of those films’ subjects.  How does an archive remain relevant in such a context, pleasing rightsholders and those represented in their collections while simultaneously embracing new technologies and user needs?  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are potential solutions on the horizon by way of new video delivery technologies that are responding to these same user needs.  As an example, several major universities, government organizations and private companies are using a video-over-IP system called Video Furnace.  Video Furnace encodes MPEG files in real time, for immediate delivery to multiple users through a static multicast IP network.  Users do not require any proprietary software, and the files are streamed in such a way so that there is no local storage of the media on the end user’s machine.  These end users are overwhelmingly satisfied with the usability of the product, a fact which Patricia O’Donnell, the Manager of UCLA’s Instructional Media Collections and Services (IMLS) has publicly stated on the product’s website; “Video Furnace works exactly as it's supposed to - it is fool proof from the standpoint of the user, and technical problems have been virtually non-existent.” [4]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;So, could moving image archives use Video Furnace?  Whether an archive could successfully implement and maintain the use of such a delivery system for their collections will depend on its individual priorities and existing mechanisms for digitization.  Video Furnace, at the admission of their sales team, is more beneficial for the end user than for the access administrator since it requires a significant amount of bandwidth as well as local storage on hard drives.  Staff members tasked with digitizing and uploading content must knowledgeable about analog-to-digital conversions and storage necessities. For an archive that is understaffed and under funded, that still that uses the “destination research center” model of access, and has no digitization equipment, Video Furnace might not be feasible.  In order to limit the access of the materials only to particular users, the archive would also have to maintain an online authentication system.  In addition to the above reasons, it would need to make an additional investment in the actual licensing of the product.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conversely, if an archive (or library, museum or cultural center with moving image holdings) has already invested some time and money into purchasing or researching this equipment, has the means to harness an already-existing (or easy to implement) authentication system, and has at least one staff member who is versed in analog-to-digital conversions and storage, Video Furnace would be a fantastic way to make those time and resource investments into an online reality.  Once an archive has the technical specifics and digitization workflow streamlined, the issue of server and delivery implementation is fairly user-friendly for the administrator.  At that point, the more ominous question of copyright and legality would be a larger concern. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The implementation of the Video Furnace system at UCLA’s IMLS caused extensive internal discussion and debate over issues of legality and copyright.   Most of the IMLS collection consists of copyrighted material, so the question of whether it has the legal right to provide a “digital copy” to teachers and students remains hazy.  The Digital Millennium Copyright Act (DMCA) and the TEACH Act were designed as provisions to Section 110(a) of the Copyright Act for educators and librarians - to “to meet the demands of the Digital Age”  (DMCA) [5] and to “facilitate and enable the performance and display of copyrighted materials for distance education.” (TEACH) [6].  But whether these acts clarify copyright issues or ease the burden of unnecessary clearances for institutions like IMLS is questionable.  As the American Library Association (ALA) points out, the DMCA “tilts strongly in favor of copyright holders.” [7]  According to Kenneth Crews, although the TEACH Act aims to create clarity and focus for institutions as to their rights, its restrictive legalese has the “ironic result … that fair use—with all of its uncertainty and flexibility—becomes of growing importance.” [8] Refreshingly, the IMLS decided that its use of the materials was entirely in the realm of fair use, and that, if challenged by rightsholders, it would use that defense in a courtroom setting.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;On the surface, it would appear that this route might not be as feasible for public sector archives that have relationships and donor deposit agreements with major studios, a sentiment which Peter Decherny has reflected; “It requires both a degree of technical competence and the support of academic institutions to venture into the shaky legal territory of fair use—both significant barriers.” [9] There is a significant dearth of available (copyrighted) feature films online, which indicates that the majority of such archives have chosen the safe route as far as their rightsholder relationships are concerned.  In the current “clearance culture,” this makes sense in the meantime.  But it doesn’t have to stay that way forever.&lt;br/&gt;At a level less obsequious than not making copyrighted assets available online at all because of a fear of “copyright maximalism” [10] is a willingness to work with studios and donors who own the copyright for material.  Many factors point towards a future where studios will see the streaming of their assets online as an asset and not a liability, as long as there are effective controls in place for such delivery.  Jon Lewis recently outlined several reasons why this trend is inevitable, one of them being that the MPAA is partnering up with major institutions like Microsoft and Comcast “in order to better monitor and control and eventually profit from the Internet delivery of feature films.” [11] Some of the issues that have been brought to the surface in the Writer’s Guild strike, where the issue of online revenue is prevalent, may also have the effect of expediting this process.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mission of moving image archives does not typically include facilitating revenue streams for studios, but the argument could be made that restricting access to those materials almost entirely is just as much a violation of that same mission.  Many archives also contain film and video material that is not only copyrighted by major studios, but is obscure enough that its likelihood of being offered for sale commercially is slim. If archives are offering a service -- broader access to that studio or rightsholder’s material that it is not their priority to make available themselves -- sanctioned streaming of their material could eventually become mainstream.  It could conceivably even become an activity that is funded BY said studios.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If this were to become a reality, the streaming model set in place by Video Furnace is an ideal method of online delivery for archives.  Rightsholders would have less of a justification to protest because of concerns about users having free digital copies of their material, because the material is never physically present on users’ computers.  Ironically, Pierce’s strategies for archives to enhance visibility of their offline collections by drawing attention to curated online content could work here in the favor of the studio.  If archives were able to provide sanctioned access to older or obscure films, then they would be providing a service for the studios connected to those films.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In his report about the TEACH Act, Kenneth Crews recognizes that librarians (and, by extension, those in related professions like archivists) are in a unique position to learn about, interpret and disseminate information about copyright and fair use.” [12] In terms of moving images, the studios are probably willing to be educated and have options presented to them by the moving image archives community.  If there is a technological mechanism that might make such options feasible, archives should be looking to embrace and not reject them as possibilities. For public domain materials where such privacy is questionable, or in the case of amateur and orphan works, Video Furnace could conceivably be used to test out the functionality of such access mechanisms.  If successful, this test could open up opportunities for future streaming of copyrighted material that is cleared for archival use with the rightsholders.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As an example of such potential in effect, the ASIFA Animation Archive is preparing for a massive dissemination of digitized cartoons to libraries, museums and educational institutions via licensed server access.  The company is mSoft, a company whose primary business is providing asset management for production companies who need to access video from multiple locations.  The fact that companies like mSoft are willing to work with an archive like ASIFA shows that there will be an upsurge of alternatives for digitized, streaming video content for archives to choose from.  In the case of ASIFA, the board of directors of the archive’s sponsoring institution (ASIFA-Hollywood) is partially made up of representatives from the major animation studios.   ASIFA’s plan is to make the server’s contents available to the studios first, as a resource for their employees.  If the studio approves of the mechanism for use in other contexts like libraries, ASIFA will be in a unique position at the forefront of providing digital access to copyrighted materials, in cooperation with, as opposed to in opposition with, rightsholders.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Rick Prelinger has stated that the ubiquity of YouTube and Google Video is in danger of leading “to a public misperception about what archives ought to be doing and what they actually do. This may mean that fewer younger scholars and media makers look to established archives for research and production.”  [13] The expansion of available online content unquestionably has the ability to change the way archives are perceived by the public.  Under the right circumstances, it could create a domino effect that increases archives’ relevance, leading to more opportunities for preservation funding and thus perpetuating a healthy cycle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1.  Rick Prelinger, &amp;quot;Remix or Rollover: Archival Paradoxes in Century 21.&amp;quot; Visions and Voices: the USC Arts and Humanities Initiative. Remixing the Archive. Annenberg Center for Communication, Los Angeles. 4 Nov. 2006.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2.  Qtd in Jon Lewis, &amp;quot;’If You Can't Protect What You Own, You Don't Own Anything’: Piracy, Privacy, and Public Relations in 21st Century Hollywood,&amp;quot; Cinema Journal 46, no. 3 (Spring 2007), 147.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3.  David Pierce, Expanding Access to Moving Image and Audio Collections in the Digital Age - Strategy and Recommendations (Library of Congress, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division; UCLA Film &amp;amp; Television Archive, 2007): 36.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;4.  Patricia O’Donnell, Video Furace 2008: Customers.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.videofurnace.com/cust/cust.php&quot;&gt;http://www.videofurnace.com/cust/cust.php&lt;/a&gt; (accessed February 4, 2008)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;5.  ALA, “DMCA: The Digital Millennium Copyright Act,” American Library Association. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ala.org/Template.cfm?Section=multitypelibrary&amp;template=/ContentManagement/ContentDisplay.cfm&amp;ContentID=144541&quot;&gt;http://www.ala.org/Template.cfm?Section=multitypelibrary&amp;amp;template=/ContentManagement/ContentDisplay.cfm&amp;amp;ContentID=144541&lt;/a&gt; (accessed February 15, 2008).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;6.  Kenneth Crews, “New Copyright Law for Distance Education: The Meaning and Importance of the TEACH Act,” Prepared for: the American Library Association, Copyright Management Center, September 30, 2002. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.copyright.iupui.edu/teach_summary.htm&quot;&gt;http://www.copyright.iupui.edu/teach_summary.htm&lt;/a&gt; (accessed February 14, 2008).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;7.  ALA &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;8.  Crews&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;9.  Peter Decherney, &amp;quot;From Fair Use to Exemption,&amp;quot; Cinema Journal 46, no. 3 (Spring 2007), 122.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;10.  Rick Prelinger, &amp;quot;Archives and Access in the 21st Century&amp;quot; Cinema Journal 46, no. 3 (Spring 2007): 117.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;11.  Lewis, 150.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;12.  Crews&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;13.  Prelinger, “Archives and Access,” 116.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2008/3/14_Light_My_Fire__Video_Furnace_and_online_access_for_moving_image_archives_files/quicktime.jpg" length="22571" type="image/jpeg"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ASIFA-Hollywood Animation Archive Strategic Plan</title>
      <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/12/15_ASIFA-Hollywood_Animation_Archive_Strategic_Plan.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">5c3b8310-c15e-45f3-9829-fcb41ab90a8c</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2007 01:46:25 -0500</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/12/15_ASIFA-Hollywood_Animation_Archive_Strategic_Plan_files/stratplan1_1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Media/object503.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding-right:10px; padding-bottom:10px; width:251px; height:188px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For the Collection Development course (MIAS 240), my final project was a Strategic Plan for the ASIFA-Hollywood Animation Archive in Burbank.  The purpose of this plan was to provide an overview of the archive’s mission, purpose, history and future goals, and to contextualize it within the framework of the broader communities of archives and animation. It set priorities and outlined a feasible timeline in which to accomplish them.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The document is a real working asset to ASIFA-Hollywood, who will use it as a guideline for both internal members and outside agencies that could potentially support its implementation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Below, I have included the Table of Contents, to give an overview of the plan’s structure.  I also included a portion of the Strengths and Weaknesses section that articulates my notion of building “archival fans.”  Lastly, I included the External Threats and Opportunities section, which showcases how I have learned to synthesize my knowledge of the role of moving image archives in the context of an evolving digital culture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/12/15_ASIFA-Hollywood_Animation_Archive_Strategic_Plan_files/stratplan1_1.jpg" length="30266" type="image/jpeg"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing a Homeland: Documentation strategies and Native American cultural heritage</title>
      <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/3/16_Visualizing_a_Homeland__Documentation_strategies_and_Native_American_cultural_heritage.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">a1c38bd9-2dfd-4451-a344-3c63b66b1966</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2007 22:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/3/16_Visualizing_a_Homeland__Documentation_strategies_and_Native_American_cultural_heritage_files/KYUK%20pic.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Media/object454_1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding-right:10px; padding-bottom:10px; width:251px; height:188px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In the American Archives and Manuscripts class (IS 431), I was introduced to a dinosaur of an appraisal theory, documentation strategy.  Largely eschewed by the traditional archival community and dismissed as “a great but impractical idea,” I saw potential for it in the moving image archives community.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This paper argues for the importance of documentation strategy for the collection and maintenance of accurate audiovisual cultural records for Native American communities.  Using the case study of the Voices and Images of Alaska (VIA) project, it argues for a reevaluation of the purpose and facility of the method for the preservation of the audiovisual cultural heritage of underrepresented native communities.  After discussing the importance of diverse visual cultural materials for a cross-section of users, it assesses the VIA project’s outreach and collection methodology and constructs a holistic evaluation of the project’s merits as well as its weaknesses.  The paper’s conclusion makes a “guide to best practices” recommendation for similar future projects that includes well-defined goals, a structured and region-specific collection approach, outreach and education elements and project maintenance strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The excerpts below represent the core of my argument.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;**NOTE** This paper received the honorable mention for the Information Studies department’s Diversity Paper Award, and is currently being prepared for publication.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two years ago I worked on a documentary called entitled Homeland: Four Portraits of Native Action, which profiled four contemporary Native American activists from four different tribes and their struggles for sovereignty and environmental justice.  The film traced the tribes’ current problems from their historical roots in order to place their modern struggle in a broader historical framework. One of my duties was to locate and license archival film and stock footage, to inform the voiceover narrative and give the viewer a visual sense of each tribe’s cultural character and legacy.  In my research, I noticed that all or most of the representation I was able to find was “outsider” material shot by major news organizations, non-native documentary filmmakers and sometimes government organizations.  This was particularly the case with the Alaskan segment of the film, which detailed an Athapascan Gwich’in tribe’s struggle with the building of an oil pipeline in the middle of caribou calving grounds of the Alaskan National Wildlife Refuge.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In attempting to preface their struggle with some visual history to elucidate their long-term relationship with the caribou, the only “insider” footage we had been able to acquire was some 16mm film from the National Archives.  The clips showed Native girls playing on a wooden teeter totter, drying caribou meat and some shots of Native women holding their babies.  In the final days of the editing process, one of our advisors from the Gwich’in tribe examined at the footage and determined that it actually depicted Inuit Natives.  I embarked on a mad search to find replacement footage, calling every archive, museum and library I could find in Alaska to see what viewing copies we could obtain.  The reason this approach is problematic is because repositories like museums and libraries are not often set up to license this type of footage because it is not within their mandate to do so.  Also, master-quality footage needs to be available for the final transfer of the film, and most of the time these types of organizations only carried poor-quality VHS viewing copies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Eventually I was able to procure a VHS viewing copy a 1973 film entitled Legends of the Tanana, which depicts the traditional passing of legends from one generation to the next by two Athapascan chiefs.  Not only did I have to go to great lengths to track down the copyright holders of this film - white filmmakers who were commissioned by the tribes to make the piece - but the only way to obtain broadcast-quality master footage was by paying for an expensive transfer of an older film element that the filmmaker had to literally dig out of his garage.  Ironically, the lengths we took to locate, license and transfer this footage allowed for this tiny visual piece of native heritage to be preserved when it otherwise would have continued to decay in a dusty, humid garage in Seattle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The above situation points to the following problems:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;	๏	Native American visual history is scattered and incomplete,&lt;br/&gt;	๏	The most immediately accessible and frequently accessed fragments of this history are covered mostly by news organizations, documentary filmmakers and other outsiders, ensuring that any study of the region that incorporates audiovisual materials will be biased,&lt;br/&gt;	๏	There is no central search mechanism for finding these resources,&lt;br/&gt;	๏	This is particularly the case in remote areas like Alaska, where complete cultural records are arguably more important due to their minimal presence in the world’s cultural memory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Looking at these elements as a whole, it becomes apparent that an inter-institutional collective effort would have to take place in order to enact a solution.  Documentation strategy is an appraisal methodology which meets these needs; although its usefulness and applicability has been questioned by traditional archivists since it was introduced in the mid-1980’s.  This methodology, however criticized and impractical in other archival environments, has the potential of a renewed sense of purpose in situations like the one outlined above.  Documentation strategy is the best way to ensure that there is a well-rounded, accessible selection of moving image cultural heritage records for native communities.  This is more broadly true for all such communities, but is especially the case in expansive rural areas like Alaska, where they are disparate and spread out across the region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Pragmatic theorization: paring down the scope of documentation strategy&lt;br/&gt;(here I lay out  the  basic tenets of the documentation strategy appraisal theory, and summarize its criticisms)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Archival adoptions: moving image holdings as cultural memory&lt;br/&gt;(in this section, I provide an overview of the orphan film movement, and talk about how it is changing the nature of appraisal for moving image collections away from film as art and towards film as cultural memory)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The state of the state of Alaska’s moving images&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At the 2006 conference of the Association of Moving Image Archivists, Mike Martz, Senior Producer at the public access TV station KYUK in Bethel, Alaska, spoke about KYUK’s moving image holdings at a panel entitled “Regional Audio-Visual Archives Case Studies.”  He spoke about preservation efforts and showed clips from their video archive, which includes 20 years of daily news broadcasts in both Yup’ik and English, locally produced pieces involving the Yup’ik community, and documentaries produced by Martz himself.  Martz showed a clip from the “Waves of Wisdom” series, which depicts Yup’ik elders describing their tribe’s values and cultures, and a rapidly decaying 1970’s video clip of some local Yup’ik children performing a traditional dance at their school.  Martz’s wife, a local schoolteacher in Bethel, frequently uses video from the KYUK collection in her classroom.  She showed this dance clip to her students one day and they recognized some of their parents – however neither the children nor their parents could perform the dance any longer.  The video element was so badly decayed that the clip was barely watchable, the ephemeral nature of a disappearing local tradition painfully obvious in the pixilated image.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In an interview, Martz extrapolated a bit on the immediacy of their preservation problem, which involves large quantities of 15-20+ year old video on the highly unstable ¾” format; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If I don’t continue to get the original material, particularly the ¾” material, converted to a more stable format, in about five years at least half of it will be unplayable.  That might be a worst-case scenario, but I keep running across reels that don’t play for one reason or another, mostly because of binder hydrolysis.  Then there’s the digital question – when can we make the jump to storing these digitally, and whether we can afford to do this here at all or does what we have need to live somewhere else. [1]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Martz has worked out a deal with the Alaskan Film Archives for some preservation and storage outsourcing – because of the uncontrolled climate conditions in the KYUK building it is acceptable for him to hold only VHS or DVD access copies and let the originals live there. Although he does what he can with the limited resources available to him, the urgency of the situation cannot be ignored.  Collections like the one at KYUK are among the more visible in the state just because of the efforts of one person (Martz), who is not even a trained archivist but comes from a production background.  There are countless situations such as this where there is no Mike Martz to ensure adequate archival procedures are implemented in the care of moving image collections.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Another somewhat urgent preservation case is the Chuck Imig video collection, which is comprised of over 5,000 reel-to-reel and video tapes shot over a 16-year period that documents the proceedings of the Alaskan Native Claims Settlement Act (ANSCA), one of the most important events in Alaska’s political history.  This includes court proceedings, tribal land meetings, and interviews with participants on both sides of the issue.  The footage is in the style of C-Span, unedited, sans commentary and blisteringly thorough in its coverage.  Former state senator Arliss Sturgulewski spoke to the importance of the collection as a cultural record, &amp;quot;We don't know much about our short history and that's wrong. I think that these videos that Imig took can be a great help in understanding where we've been, so we know where we are as we move ahead in solving other big issues.&amp;quot; [2]  Imig feels the people at the meetings responded to the camera, as he states in this news story, “Videotape was a new technology at the time, and Imig thinks the camera became a player in the many ANSCA and ANILCA talks. Everyone was very aware of the camera, he said, ‘and it brought out the truth in people.’” [3] The “official” ANSCA proceedings are documented in the public record, but the inherent tensions, character nuances and tone of the debates cannot be expressed in government court documents or press coverage.  Coverage of the tribal land meetings is also unique, as access was granted to Imig due to the fact that he was commissioned by Don Wright, former president of the former Alaska Federation of Natives.  This insider-granted footage has the potential to enforce the notion that these communities have at times straddled their oppression, as Richard Jennings describes; “Alaska Natives have, both prior to colonization and through linkages to the larger society, shaped and reshaped their won social structures with unusual savvy.” [4]  The Imig collection is almost at critical mass in that it is reaching that stage of a video collection’s life where preservation is absolutely crucial.  This is a delicate, complicated and expensive process that will require collaboration between Imig and a sponsoring archive.  Whether that will happen may well depend on a mechanized strategy that encourages this kind of cooperation, as well as gives the collections in its scope the visibility required to seek further preservation funding.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The particular nature of Alaska in terms of its countryside and cultural complexities make it a difficult subject for study and interpretation.  Some of the forces that play into these complexities are 1) Alaska’s geographically vast landscape, 2) its relatively new statehood and prior history of colonization and imperialism, 3) the diversity of its Native peoples and 4) the inherent tension between the cultural priorities of Natives and the outsiders that seek to study them.  Michael Jennings has written about the difficulties of researching Alaskan Native cultures; “Strange bedfellows, hidden motivations, strategic interventions, and unintended consequences intersect with larger philosophical and cultural currents in the success or failure of any given [research] initiative.  Understanding this multifaceted and interdisciplinary situation is no simple proposition for a researcher.”  [5]  Western concepts of ownership also fall victim to these kinds of communication lapses; Martz spoke about some Native Alaskan’s self-proclaimed “traditional imperative” that they invoke when refusing to sign a release.  Many of KYUK’s holdings that depict Native subjects are not licensable to outside sources, which Martz sees as problematic for access.  There is no clear cut solution to these clashing imperatives.  But a documentation strategy that encourages discussion and cooperation between Native and non-native institutions could potentially approach a level of understanding in terms of complex notions such as copyright and intellectual property. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The above examples each point to a different reason that a documentation strategy could be effective in the identification and collocation of disparate sets of moving image archive holdings.  There is a case study that warrants examination in terms of the real-world applicability of such an undertaking.  In 2001, the Alaska Moving Image Preservation Association (AMIPA) received a grant from the Save America’s Treasures program, a public-private partnership fund dispersed by the National Park Service and the National Trust for Historic Preservation, for a project entitled Voices and Images of Alaska (VIA).   Although the project was intuitively “demand-driven”, it nonetheless follows the pattern of a well-implemented, effective and largely successful example of a documentation strategy.  The project was designed as a “long-term strategy to identify and protect Alaska's culturally and historically valuable film, video and audio collections.”  [6]  Although the scope of the project extends beyond cultural and native material – AMIPA’s mandate states that it aims to save all Alaskan moving images – Alaska’s largely regional nature and the predominance of seven major Native Alaskan groups ensure that the VIA project encapsulates these materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Voices and Images of Alaska project: approaching the right idea&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The VIA project follows all of Samuels’ initial guidelines for documentation strategy:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(1)   Topic selection and definition: AMIPA defined the topic as Alaskan moving image material.&lt;br/&gt;(2)   Site establishment and advisory board formation: AMIPA was designated as the site, an archivist was assigned to direct the project and the advisory board was formed out of a selection of ten representatives from local archives and libraries, schools and universities, and historical associations. &lt;br/&gt;(3)   Assessment of available documentation and plan implementation: the first phase of the project was an inventory and assessment plan, which included a survey of the more “well-known” collections from archives, news organizations, libraries and museums around the state.  The second phase of the project involved outreach to fill in the gaps where there was missing representation of specific cultures, types of footage (i.e. amateur and home movie vs. scenic stock footage vs. news and documentary footage, etc) and areas of Alaskan culture and economy.  &lt;br/&gt;(4)   Organization and placement of the information: the final phase of the project is the publication, in print and electronically, of an inventory document with copyright, format and cataloguing data for the entirety of the project’s findings.  The catalog will also be integrated with the Library of Congress’s Moving Image Collections (MIC) database, which ensures broad dissemination of its findings to a broad cross-section of researchers as well as the moving image archive community.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project goals state that its mission is twofold: first to address the preservation needs of the holdings as a whole, and second to provide a complete record of Alaska’s visual history for research use.  In order to effect these goals, the VIA project has harnessed their tradition of outreach to facilitate the location of collections and to promote their proper care and maintenance by educating collection holders.  According to archivist and project director Kevin Tripp, “We do a certain level of outreach anyway … partly through fundraising activities and partly because it serves the community better … VIA is a more formalized mechanism, that helped grow our organization statewide.”  [7]  The project funded two conferences in 2002 and 2005, each with a different focus and set of topics, panels and speakers.  The 2002 conference, entitled “Sharing the Knowledge, Sharing the Tools”, stressed the fundamentals of media preservation, storage and climate concerns, and basic cataloguing training.  Jim Hubbard and Mona Jimenez from Independent Media Arts Preservation (IMAP) provided training in FileMaker Pro with a specific VIA template, with the goal of making cataloguing simple for some of the untrained non-archivists and facilitating information sharing between repositories.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2005 conference, “Voices and Images of Alaska 2005”, developed out of a response from attendees of the first conference.  According to Tripp, “we had asked people in the 2002 conference what they wanted to see from us next time.  The two concepts that were highlighted were copyright issues and complicated ownership issues that surround Alaska Native cultural material.” AMIPA brought in John McKay, a local copyright lawyer with a special interest in moving archives, and Dr. Rosita Worl, an Alaskan Tlingit woman who holds a PhD in Anthropology: “It was an excellent interchange – they both spoke independently and then it turned into a dialogue between the two, about how western copyright concepts fell apart relative to these more traditional concepts of ownership and how to try and make these connections work.” These two conferences supplemented the entire project’s goals by creating a collective sense of purpose between all participants.  In the sense that educational aspect is a crucial part of their strategy, VIA extends beyond the traditional definition of documentation strategy, arguably in a way that enriches and improves it to promote better relationships and communication between participating institutions.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Another unique way that VIA approached its strategy was in its incorporation of screenings and fundraising events throughout the process to bolster collection efforts during the “filling in the gaps” phase of the project.  Once again capitalizing on its honed outreach practices, Tripp would organize targeted screenings and involve the media when a particularly valuable piece of footage or collection came in, “Periodically we’d get a hold of something interesting and pass it along to the media so we could get some visibility and that would in turn bring more to our door.  … public screening events, or fundraising events – often times they are the same thing – served to bring collections to us.”  One such screening involved a home movie collection by a Native Alaskan man from the remote village of Barrow that depicted traditional seasonal hunting and gathering, “To the outside world it’s incredibly exotic because they are hunting walrus, whale and caribou.  But the feel of it is totally different than a lot of documentary footage because it’s just these guys out hunting with their friends.” Due to the fact that it was a rarity for men from this region to have a camera in the 1960’s, the acquisition of this piece of footage was a small but important example of the success of documentation strategy to complete the visual cultural record in this particular case.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Perhaps the most notorious single piece of footage that came in and was selected for exhibition was another amateur 16mm film reel that was donated from a man in California who had bought the film at a garage sale.  Upon noticing that a few of the cans were labeled “Alaska”, he contacted AMIPA and shipped them the reels on his own dime.  Tripp described the mounting excitement from he and the other AMIPA staff when they realized the film dated back to the 1930’s.  Based on this alone -- pre-war footage constituted a major gap in the VIA collection -- he organized a screening, but then realized upon a projection inspection that there was more to the footage than they had originally assessed, “it had this nice sequence that with a little bit of detective work we determined was Will Rogers and Wiley Post in Anchorage in 1935, the day before their fatal plane crash.  And it’s probably the last motion picture footage that was shot of either one of them.”  This piece of footage is an example of how AMIPA’s ongoing outreach strategies further enriched the VIA’s collection development.  According to Tripp, “although it was short, it was such a historic piece of film.  This was such an important story nationwide, but it particularly resonated here in Alaska because it happened here.  This piece of footage got us a LOT of media visibility and led to a lot of telephone calls and a lot of interesting film came our way after that, amateur collections.”  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The inclusion of amateur collections speaks to one of the central purposes of documentation strategy – to ensure that the cultural record is not biased in favor of dominant power structures and represents all members of a given region.  Sam Kula, former president of the Association of Moving Image Archivists and author of the only book on moving image appraisal methods, included a brief chapter devoted to the applicability of traditional appraisal methods to film archives.  His one mention of documentation strategy, however brief, speaks to this very issue, &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The effort to develop a bottom-up approach has given rise to the concept of documentation strategy … what this approach signals to moving image archivists is the need to move outside the boundaries of the moving images industries to reach out to amateur and independent image-makers, all types of artists working in film and video and image-making on the margins of society, to ensure that their collections are truly reflective of the entire society. [8]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this way, the medium specificity of the VIA project promotes the applicability of documentation strategies to a particular kind of moving image project – one that assesses a regional culture where traditions are largely oral, communities are distant from one another and the presence of moving image material is scarce.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;… (problems encountered, preservation issues with certain types of collections, current status of the project) … &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conclusion&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Perhaps the spirit of cooperation inherent in the VIA project speaks to its roots in Alaska, with its closer proximity to Canada than the rest of the United States.  In his book Documenting Localities, Richard Cox argues that American archivists have trouble approaching purposeful collaboration, but that Canadian archivists’ concept of “total archives” promotes it.  He quotes a Canadian archival group report, which defines total archives as those that “actively acquire both the unofficial records and an extensive range of private materials in all documentary media bearing on the life of their institution or region.” [9] This certainly seems to be in line with the mission and purpose of the VIA project, which appears rooted in a sense of cooperation and local imperative that other archives could stand to learn from.  Cox lays out a set of guidelines for the proper implementation of documentation strategies for localities, that while somewhat streamlined still appear exasperatingly broad in scope.  It may be better to propose documentation strategy to archivists with baby steps, and limiting the scope of the elements to be documented by record type might be the best way to do this.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Beyond limiting by record type, the importance of a structured approach to documentation cannot be over-stressed, nor can the importance of follow-through to ensure that the strategy’s results are made accessible and updated over time.  This access should include localized publication in both print and electronic form to ensure that communities without web or computer access can view them, and should also be extended to larger databases like MIC to provide access to the wider public via already established mechanisms.  The producers of Homeland: Four Portraits of Native Action are now enacting an outreach and education plan that involves using segments of the film with modules that will serve to educate local tribes in strategies for empowering themselves.  It is a shame that projects like the VIA project did not exist at the time of that film’s production, as they may have served to provide a better selection of images to these communities.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this paper is to provoke a discussion among holders of Native American moving image material.  Approaching a strategy toward the documentation of their holdings need not be overly complicated, but will require effort and collaboration.  As writer Tom Kizzia has stated, “Our images of the Indian – primitive, savage, mystic, saint, ghost – have generally said more about changing American attitudes toward the continent than about the changing realities of Native American life.”  [10]  Perhaps its time for moving image archivists to take the lead in ensuring that future attitudes about these communities are informed by the widest cross-section of information that it is within our power to present.  This is the essential mission of all archivists, to provide as complete a historic record as possible.  If that means focusing on one type of record at a time, there is no reason why that record can’t be visual. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Mike Martz (Archivist, KYUK-TV), in discussion with the author, February 2007.  All other quotes attributed to Martz are derived from this interview.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Angela Unruh, “Archived video of Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act given to public” KTUU.com, October 13, 2006, &lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ktuu.com/Global/story.asp?S=5681892&amp;nav=menu510_5_7&quot;&gt;http://www.ktuu.com/Global/story.asp?S=5681892&amp;amp;nav=menu510_5_7&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3.  Beth Bragg, “Land-claims history is at the mercy of fragile videotapes” Anchorage Daily News, October 28, 2006 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adn.com/news/alaska/story/8356308p-8251785c.html&quot;&gt;http://www.adn.com/news/alaska/story/8356308p-8251785c.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;4.  Michael Jennings, Alaska Native Political Leadership and Higher Education: One University, Two Universes. (Walnut Creek: AltaMira Press, 2004), 7.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;5.  Michael Jennings, Alaska Native Political Leadership and Higher Education, 6.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;6. See the description of the project &lt;a href=&quot;http://us.f824.mail.yahoo.com/ym/ShowFolder?YY=52699&amp;y5beta=yes&amp;box=Inbox&amp;YN=1&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on AMIPA’s website:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amipa.org/VIA_Project.html&quot;&gt;http://www.amipa.org/VIA_Project.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;7.  Kevin Tripp (Archivist, Alaska Moving Image Preservation Association), in discussion with the author, March 2007.  All other quotes attributed to Tripp are derived from this interview.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;8. Sam Kula, Assessing the Archival and Monetary Value of Film and Video Records. (Lanham: Scarecrow Press, 2003), 33-34.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;9. Quoted in Richard Cox, Documenting Localities: A Practical Model for American Archivists and Manuscript Curators (Lanham: Scarecrow Press, 2001), 48.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;10. Tom Kizzia, The Wake of the Unseen Object (New York: Henry Holt, 1991), 6.&lt;br/&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/3/16_Visualizing_a_Homeland__Documentation_strategies_and_Native_American_cultural_heritage_files/KYUK%20pic.jpg" length="131786" type="image/jpeg"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calvin and the New Librarian: Musings on the importance of Google Book Search</title>
      <link>https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/3/16_Calvin_and_the_New_Librarian__Musings_on_the_importance_of_Google_Book_Search.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">a9a02735-f4d6-47d5-802a-788fd731baa8</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2007 01:37:27 -0400</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/3/16_Calvin_and_the_New_Librarian__Musings_on_the_importance_of_Google_Book_Search_files/hitcalvin.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Media/object453_1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding-right:10px; padding-bottom:10px; width:251px; height:188px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;This excerpt, written for Information Structures (IS 260) is the only section that does not deal directly with moving image archives.  I included it here because it is an example of the type of user-centric thinking that I believe is currently lacking in the moving image archiving community.  It speaks to the movement towards digitization in all aspects of culture, and why all archivists should consequently pay attention to this movement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The assignment for this final paper was to assess the validity of, and argue for or against, one statement from a list.  The statement I chose to respond to was “Does Google Book Search change everything?”  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Google is far from the only entity that is embarking on mass book digitization, but its status as the most commercially and publicly visible entity brings it to the forefront of the debates about changing library strategies.  In the broader world of library and information sciences, Google Book Search is paradigmatically representative of a movement towards the digitization of content, its full text searchable by keyword or user-created tags and metadata.  Debates over the implications of this movement for librarians have invoked several important questions.  Does Google Book Search change “everything”?  To determine this, it is necessary to define the notion of “everything” as it pertains to this issue.  “Everything” includes:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;	๏	The role of ontological concepts as a broader philosophical means of organizing the world’s library holdings&lt;br/&gt;	๏	The future of controlled vocabularies and subject classification, both in a broad philosophical sense and as a pragmatic priority for librarians and cataloguers&lt;br/&gt;	๏	The usefulness and level of priority given to keeping quantities of physical book holdings in libraries&lt;br/&gt;	๏	The role of librarians and their relationships to users&lt;br/&gt;	๏	The research priorities of users&lt;br/&gt;	๏	The form and focus of the world’s scholarly and professional output as a whole.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In light of this definition, Google Book Search is in the process of changing “everything,” as evidenced by changing priorities at the Library of Congress and the growth and popularity of open source content and websites that allow and encourage it.  That being said, these consequences are only symptomatic of the evolving needs of the public.  The changes being put in place at the Library of Congress and the resulting debates about their implications for librarians are well-documented, and more symptomatic than diagnostic.   The most diagnostic factor in assessing the level to which Google Book Search affects the global sphere of information search and retrieval is the changing face of the user.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As the American Council of Learned Societies stated in a recent web module, “It is not just the collection of data—digital or otherwise—that matters: at least as important is the activity that goes on around it, contributes to it, and eventually integrates with it.” [1] The exponential growth of a new generation of users who not only prefer, but nearly exclusively use keyword and user-based searches in their research is the most significant rationale for librarians to follow Google’s lead in the valuation of open digital content.  They are the impetus for the entire open content movement, and the model on which librarians should base not only their current priorities, but their future purpose and function.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;LOC changes – turn and face the strain&lt;br/&gt;[Discussion of changes at the Library of Congress, arguments of Thomas Mann]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Meet Calvin, “the new user”&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In his papers devoted to the future of cataloguing, Thomas Mann spends ample time critically developing the miscreant form of a student who prefers web research, who “has a term paper due quickly, who does not want to leave her cozy dorm room and trudge all the way to the library, who does not have time to read entire books in any event, who wants only English language material, and who cannot be bothered with anything that does not come up immediately in a Google search.” [2] Although spiteful in its tone, Mann’s reaction was fueled by Marcum’s ostentatious development of a character she called “Calvin” at a speech given in 2006 in Michigan, where she states, &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hobbes looked at Calvin, and they both nodded–yes, there’s an easier way. Go to the Web, get the Google search box, type in a keyword, and get back not catalog information, and not advice, but information itself–the stuff you really need to write a term paper. On the Web he could do that without having to go to the library or anywhere else outside his dorm room, except that candy-bar machine. Calvin really liked that. [3]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Calvin, although somewhat maliciously aligned in statements like the one above, is nevertheless a formidable character that will more and more become the model for the type of user that will be in need of the information that it is a librarian’s purpose to make accessible.  He is based on the average undergraduate user, who, while seemingly undervalued by librarians like Mann, is the pool from which future graduate students will be pulled.  By extension, future PhD candidates and university professors, doctors, scholars and all other professional-level users of information content will be pulled from this group as well.  So for the purposes of discussions about the importance of the user, it does not necessarily behoove Mann to discredit the undergraduate student.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;So how, or more importantly, how well, do these “new’ undergraduates conduct research?  To a large extent, a student’s work is only as good as the information to which they have access.  The level of access to information, the depth of that information and its originality in comparison to other students’ work are affected by the process by which research is conducted.  It is directly correlated not only to the amount of work that a student puts into the process but the variety of that work.      &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The different levels of research work that a student puts into a given paper, presentation, or project can be considered “currency” to a large extent, with these different levels representing the amount of currency they are willing to invest in their project.  Each time a student has to leave the comfort of their dorm or apartment and physically travel the library could represent a set amount of currency. Each time that student has to fill out a special form at the library to request items that are kept behind a desk is another set, having to use equipment like microfiche readers is another, the wait for interlibrary loans and transfers is yet another.  In one survey of college student’s research methods by Karl Fast and D. Grant Campbell, they described a subset of these levels of “currency”, just within the constraints of using an OPAC interface: “The OPAC … suggests delay while manipulating the complicated features such as controlled vocabularies, or authorized headings; delay while acquiring the necessary skill set to use these features more efficiently; and the delay inherent in moving from the surrogates to the documents themselves.” [4]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ideal, most well-rounded student, who is engaged with their subject and wants a breadth of sources and materials, will “invest” well in their research, employing a combination of all of the above levels of “currency,” plus a healthy dose of internet searching.  But it is arguable that most students (and even professional researchers) would ideally like to be able to achieve this source breadth with the most minimal investment, i.e. the “cheapest” way possible.  This means, essentially, using internet resources almost exclusively.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Survey Says … Google&lt;br/&gt;[Discussion of surveys of college users, the results of a personal survey of a group of undergraduate students from my ENG 4W class]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conclusion&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The central fear that writers like Mann seem to evoke is one of decentralization – the onset of the digital library and efforts like Google Book Search invoke not only pragmatic questions about the librarian’s essential daily duties, but their very usefulness, integrity and the relevance of advanced education and experience.  Mann even acknowledges this fear in a moment of lucid self-awareness; “Professional librarians who raise objections to the abandonment of cataloging and classification [are] dismissed as dinosaurs whose ‘resistance to change’ springs not from their concern for the maintenance of high professional standards, but from a selfish fear of losing job security.”  [5] But professional standards don’t need to be abandoned completely as much as they need to, have to be modified to adapt to changing needs and technologies.  As long-time cataloguer James Weinheimer states, “If libraries are to play an important role in the World Wide Web, which I believe they should, it will be through their catalogs and the methods they choose to merge their catalog records with the wider world of metadata.”  [6] Not only should librarians find ways to merge traditional cataloguing standards with newer keyword and user-based search metadata, but they should advance their training in digital technologies and continue their efforts towards digitizing their own, unique subset of book holdings.  In addition to the Library of Congress’s obvious move in this direction, small, progressive libraries are showing signs of this evolution by listing their holdings on LibraryThing or linking up with the Open Content Alliance to point users to digitized texts, as in the case outlined on the Prelinger Library’s blog:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Today is a bit of a milestone. A visitor pulled Finding the Worth While in California (1916) off the shelf and asked if she could scan a page from it to take with her to use in a project. Rick recognized from the bookmark that it had been scanned through the Internet Archive. He downloaded a PDF of the entire book for the visitor and put it on her flash drive. Thus our library became a functioning digital as well as analog book resource. [7]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is the librarian of the future, who seeks to understand the user’s needs, who values wide access to information, and who acts as a facilitator for digital content.  Let the Calvins of the world take comfort in this idea and look forward to the day when the boundaries between the dorm room and the reading room are blurred, but there is space for both.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. American Council of Learned Societies, Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities &amp;amp; Social Sciences, “A Grand Challenge for the Humanities and Social Sciences,” &lt;a href=&quot;http://cnx.org/content/m14141/latest/&quot;&gt;http://cnx.org/content/m14141/latest/&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Thomas Mann, “Will Google’s Keyword Searching Eliminate the Need for LC Cataloging and Classification?,” AFSCME 2910, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guild2910.org/searching.htm&quot;&gt;http://www.guild2910.org/searching.htm&lt;/a&gt; (accessed February 23, 2007).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3. Quoted in Thomas Mann, “What is Going on at the Library of Congress?”, 7.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;4. Karl V. Fast and D. Grant Campbell, “’I Still Prefer Google’: University Student Perceptions of Searching OPACS and the Web,” presentation to the ASIST 2004 Annual Meeting, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.asis.org/Conferences/AMO4/abstracts/137.html&quot;&gt;http://www.asis.org/Conferences/AMO4/abstracts/137.html&lt;/a&gt; (accessed March 8, 2007), 144.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;4. Thomas Mann, “Will Google’s Keyword Searching Eliminate the Need for LC Cataloging and Classification?”&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;5. James Weinheimer, “An Open Reply to ‘What is Going on at the Library of Congress?’ by Thomas Mann,” E-Prints in Library and Information Science, &lt;a href=&quot;http://eprints.rclis.org/archive/00006741/01/Response_to_Thomas_Mann.pdf&quot;&gt;http://eprints.rclis.org/archive/00006741/01/Response_to_Thomas_Mann.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (accessed February 23,2007).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;6. Megan Prelinger, comment on “First Digital Book Distributed,” The Prelinger Library Blog, comment posted December 6, 2006, &lt;a href=&quot;http://prelingerlibrary.blogspot.com/2006/12/first-digital-book-distributed.html&quot;&gt;http://prelingerlibrary.blogspot.com/2006/12/first-digital-book-distributed.html&lt;/a&gt;  (accessed March 12, 2006).</description>
      <enclosure url="https://www.stephaniesapienza.com/sapienza-ucla-portfolio/Paper_Excerpts/Entries/2007/3/16_Calvin_and_the_New_Librarian__Musings_on_the_importance_of_Google_Book_Search_files/hitcalvin.jpg" length="19733" type="image/jpeg"/>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
